<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The observation of the three great festivals asserted in the Christian church and that objection answered, from Gal 4. 10, 11., and also the right manner of the observance of them made known, in a sermon, preach'd on Easter-Day / by Richard Stafford.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42800</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875771</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93749)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2295:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The observation of the three great festivals asserted in the Christian church and that objection answered, from Gal 4. 10, 11., and also the right manner of the observance of them made known, in a sermon, preach'd on Easter-Day / by Richard Stafford.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by E. Whitlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Galatians IV, 10-11 --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians III, 4 --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Fasts and feasts --  Church of England.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE OBSERVATION OF THE Three Great Feſtivals Aſſerted IN THE Chriſtian Church: AND THAT <hi>Objection Anſwered,</hi> From <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10, 11. AND ALSO The Right Manner of the Obſervance of Them made known.</p>
            <p>In a SERMON, Preach'd on <hi>Eaſter-Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Stafford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>E. Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:152400:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152400:2"/>Col. iii. 1.</bibl>
               <q>If ye then be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſitteth on the Right Hand of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AND Moſes <hi>ſaid unto the People, Remember this day in which ye came out from</hi> Egypt, <hi>out of the Houſe of Bondage; for by Strength of Hand the Lord brought you out from this Place. There ſhall no leavened Bread be eaten. This day came ye out in the Month</hi> Abib: <hi>thou ſhalt therefore keep this Ordinance</hi> (that is, of the Paſſeover which He then Inſtituted) <hi>in his Seaſon, from Year to Year,</hi> Exod. 13. 3, 4, 10. Again it is Recorded in the foregoing Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Exod. 12. 42. It is a Night to be much obſerved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord for bringing them out from the Land of</hi> Egypt; <hi>this is that Night of the Lord to be obſerved of all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in their Generations.</hi> From all this put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether it may be truly Reaſon'd and Inferr'd, That if the Eternal Spirit, who is of the ſame Mind <hi>Yeſterday, to day, and for ever,</hi> and knows what are the things which are pleaſing unto God, and He doth require of us; did (as we ſee here He did) command the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to remember the Day in which they came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Houſe of Bondage; and it doth particularly ſet down the Month in the which it was, with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, <hi>Thou ſhalt therefore keep this Ordinance in his Seaſon from Year to Year;</hi> having before mention'd that it was a <hi>Night to be much obſerved unto the Lord;</hi> yea, it is repeated and enforced again, <hi>That it was to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152400:3"/> of all the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in their Generations.</hi> How much more ought all Chriſtians to remember that Day, in which Jeſus Chriſt their Head and Saviour roſe again from the Dead (for hereby He was <hi>declared to be the Son of God with Power, according to the Spirit of Holineſs by the Reſurrection from the Dead,</hi> Rom. 1. 4.) whereby He accompliſhed as Great, yea, a much Greater and more Eſpecial Part of our Redemption, as God did work a Deliverance to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by bringing them out of the Land of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And as upon that Account He is the Lord their God, ſo upon the alike and much greater Account He is the God of us Chriſtians alſo, by Redeeming us, by his Son Jeſus Chriſt, from <hi>Spiritual Egypt,</hi> the Bondage of <hi>Satan,</hi> Sin and Death. And as this ſame Redemption wrought, and accompliſhed by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead, is ſo much better than that Deliverance of our Fore-fathers out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> (which was a leſſer Type and Figure of this) as it hath by the Benefits and Priviledges hereby accrued and devolved unto Mankind, <hi>obtained a much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Name than that;</hi> There is alike and greater Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the Time of Jeſus Chriſt his Riſing from the Dead, ſhould be remembred together with the Month, for it was about the ſame Time that they did receive the Paſſeover, and did Yearly Commemorate their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that this <hi>Ordinance alſo ſhould be kept in his Seaſon from Year to Year.</hi> And as Jeſus Chriſt did ariſe again, <hi>in the end of the Sabbath, as it began to dawn towards the firſt Day of the Week,</hi> Mat. 28. 1. and in another Evangeliſt it is ſaid, <hi>That it was the firſt Day of the Week early when it was yet dark.</hi> John 20. 1. The Holy Ghoſt by recording it here in theſe two Places, in ſo very a particular manner, that we may gueſs and know within a quarter of an Hour the exact time when it was, doth hereby ſignifie, <hi>That that ſame Night and Day between the end of the Sabbath, and the firſt Day of the Week, or rather the twilight, is a Night and a Day, or a Twilight, to be much obſerved unto the Lord for raiſing his Son Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead.</hi> This is that Night and Day of the Lord, or the Twilight, to be obſerved of all Chriſtians, who name the Name of Jeſus Chriſt in their Generations. For this Thing of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152400:3"/> Twilight, or Dawning of the Day ſeems to have been foretold by the Prophet <hi>Zechariah; And it ſhall come to paſs in that day that the Light ſhall not be clear nor dark: But it ſhall be one Day, which ſhall be known unto the Lord, not Day nor Night,</hi> Zech. 14. 6, 7. This was exactly ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill'd. <hi>But it ſhall come to paſs at Evening Time it ſhall be Light.</hi> It is evident from the Fourth Verſe of this ſame Chapter, that Chriſt herein was propheſied of. And tho theſe Words do chiefly ſeem to have Reſpect unto Chriſt's laſt Coming to Judgment, which is yet to come, yet they were in a leſs Degree fulfilled in the Time of his Reſurrection from the Dead, it being an uſual Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod with the Scriptures of Truth, to have their fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a leſſer Degree, and then in a Greater and more Univerſal manner, like as it is with the Fruits of the Earth; ſome few of theſe are commonly ripe before the General and Greater Quantity are ſo. As I could Illuſtrate this further, and make it more evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the other and parallel Places of Scripture, which in ſuch manner have been interpreted to have been fulfilled by the Divinely Inſpired Apoſtles. But this would be to go too much aſide from my Subject and intended Matter; for whereas it is written, <hi>And his Feet ſhall ſtand in that Day upon the Mount of Olives, which is before</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>on the East, and the Mount of Olives ſhall cleave in the midſt thereof, towards the Eaſt, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the West,</hi> Zech. 14. 4. This was then ſomewhat fulfill'd, (tho I do withall believe that it will be yet more Litterally and Univerſally fulfill'd at his future Coming to Judgment) <hi>When Jeſus cried with a loud Voice, and yeilded up the Ghoſt, and behold the Vail of the Temple was rent in twain from the top to the bottom, and the Earth did quake, and the Rocks rent,</hi> Mat. 27. 50, 51. For all this comes very near, and is much alike to the Mount of Olives, (where or near to which his Crucifixion was) cleaving in the midſt thereof. It is a wonderful thing to conſider how the Decrees and Purpoſes of God were made and ordered, and fixed as to theſe material Circumſtances of Place and Time: Inſtances whereof are ſo very many throughout the Scripture, that it is ſuperfluous to give any other than what are pertinent to our preſent Matter in Hand.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152400:4"/>
            <p>As to the Circumſtance of Time, <hi>And it came to paſs at the end of the Four Hundred and Thirty Years</hi> (which was the time of their ſojourning in <hi>Egypt)</hi> even the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame Day (take notice of that) <hi>it came to paſs that all the Hoſts of the Lord went out from the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>Exod, 12. 41. It is a Night to be much obſerved unto the Lord.</hi> And ſo it came to paſs that in thoſe very Days, and in the ſame time of the Year (for all the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> were then gone up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be preſent at this their Yearly Commemoration of their Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to obſerve the Feaſt of the Paſſeover) That Jeſus Chriſt, according to the Fleſh, ſuffer'd, and was put to Death on the Croſs, if not on the Mount of Olives, yet on Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> which perhaps was a part thereof, or very near unto it. The Goſpel ſaith, <hi>That the Place was nigh to Jeruſalem.</hi> And he aroſe again. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, all this great Thing was tranſacted at the ſelf ſame time of the Year, in which that was, as it doth abundantly and evidently appear from the Hiſtory and Narration of all the four Evangeliſts concerning it. And therefore it is a Night and a Day, when in the Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi>'s Phraſe, it was not Night, nor yet Day, it being Twilight, not Dark, nor yet Light, to be much obſerved unto the Lord; yea, to be obſerved by all Chriſtians, and by all that call themſelves ſo in their Generations.</p>
            <p>Moſt certain it is, That it was much obſerved unto the Lord by the Apoſtles, who had ſeen Jeſus Chriſt in the Fleſh, and to <hi>whom He ſhewed himſelf alive after his Paſſion; he being ſeen o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them Fourty Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and ſpeaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God.</hi> Which things are not written and recorded, but by their framing their Practice accordingly, and by their aſſembling together on the firſt Day of the Week, in Memory and Acknowledgment that their Lord did on that Day riſe from the Dead. Which alſo is the very Reaſon of that Change, which hath been made of the Sabbath from the Seventh Day, which the <hi>Jews</hi> kept Holy in Memory of the Creation; becauſe that God had finiſhed his Work, and reſted on the Seventh Day, and ſanctified it to our Obſervation of the ſame Day of Reſt, ſeparated and ſet apart for the more Solemn and Univerſal Worſhip now on the firſt Day of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152400:4"/> the Week, which is called the Lord's-Day. This is in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance how that our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt roſe from the Dead on the firſt day of the Week. And if it hath occaſion'd the Change of the Sabbath Day throughout the whole Year, well then may one particular Lord's Day in the Year be obſerved in an eminent Manner above, and more than the other Lords Days; and ſo it is done at this Day by the Churches throughout the Chriſtian World. <hi>This is the Day which the Lord hath made, we will rejoyce, and be glad in it,</hi> Pſal. 118. 28. We read often in the Goſpel, of the Apoſtles and <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> aſſembling together on the firſt Day of the Week; and <hi>John</hi> ſaith in the <hi>Revelations, That he was in the Spirit on the Lord's Day.</hi> Now it is a Rule and Maxim, laid down by <hi>Augustine,</hi> an Eminent Preacher and Writer in the Church of God, a Learned and Holy Man in his Generation; <hi>That whatever was practiſed by the Apostles themſelves, and by the Generality of Chriſtians for the firſt Three Hundred Iears,</hi> (this being long before, the Corruptions, Errors and Additions of Popery came in, for they came in about the Six Hundredth Year after Chriſt) <hi>and the ſame is agreeable to the Cano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ical Scriptures</hi> (as the Obſervation of the Feaſt of the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, commonly called <hi>Eaſter</hi> is Which is further manifeſt from the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches about the exact time of its Obſervance; for both did agree that it was to be kept) this ſaith <hi>Auſtine, We ought to receive for Divine and Apoſtolick Inſtitution.</hi> And truly, when we read in the Scripture it ſelf, yea, in the Goſpel; <hi>And when the Day of Pentecoſt</hi> (which we now commonly call <hi>Whitſuntide) was fully come,</hi> Acts 2. 1. <hi>Chriſt our Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over is now riſen, therefore let us now keep the Feaſt</hi> (the Apoſtle hereby ſeems to mean the very Feaſt of his Reſurrection) <hi>not with the Leaven of Malice and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but with the unleavened Bread of Sincerity and Truth.</hi> Here is enough to juſtifie, even under the Goſpel Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and in this Goſpel-Day the Obſervation of thoſe three Great Feſtivals, as is the Nativity and Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt on the Day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> like as the <hi>Jews,</hi> the antient Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of the Father, did obſerve their Feaſt of Unlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened Bread, <hi>the Feaſt of Weeks,</hi> and the <hi>Feaſt of Faber
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152400:5"/> cles, Deut.</hi> 16. 16. Theſe were their three times of their appearing before the Lord at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which God hath Inſtituted by <hi>Moſes;</hi> altho with and amongſt them they had brought in their new Moons, and other Days of their own Inſtitution, as alſo ſome <hi>Gentile</hi> Rites and Obſervations; the Continuance whereof amongſt thoſe who were converted unto, and had received the Chriſtian Faith, The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reproves, when he ſaith, <hi>Ye obſerve Days and Months, and Times, and Years, I am afraid of you, leſt I have beſtowed on you Labour in vain,</hi> Gal. 4. 10, 11. That all this is chiefly, if not only meant of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cuſtoms, Ceremonies, and Obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, appears from the foregoing Verſe, wherein he ſpeaks unto them on this wiſe; <hi>But now after that ye have known God, or rather are known of God, how turn ye again to the weak and beggarly Elements, wherein ye deſire again to be in Bondage.</hi> Importing, as if it was an Incongruous and Unſeemly Thing, that after they had known the High, Spiritual, Free, and Inward Diſpenſation of the Goſpel, they ſhould again Apoſtatize and fall back to the Law, which was made up of mean, low, carnal, outward and ſlaviſh Obſervations and Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>From all this conſider'd together, we may learn and be inſtructed to beware of Extreams, or of running from one wrong Extream to another, or leaſt, under pretence of avoiding both Extreams, which are bad, We reject alſo the Truth, which lies in the middle of them both; for as when God had Inſtituted by <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuch and ſuch Feaſts to be obſerved amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> they did further bring in ſome Feaſts and Obſervations of their own. Now, in this caſe, if any Zealots or Godly Reformers, inſtead of Purging out, laying aſide, and abrogating theſe laſt, they ſhould go on alſo to neglect and caſt off all the former, they would not have done ſafely, nor yet well. In like manner it is at this day. There are in the Chriſtian Church three Great and Solemn Feſtivals aforemention'd; which, by the uſage from the beginning of Chriſtianity, and by being mention'd therein, and alſo being agreeable unto the Goſpel, They ſeem to be of Divine and Apoſtolical Inſtitution; and as ſuch they ought to be obſerved unto the Lord; yea, to be obſerv'd of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians in their Generations.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152400:5"/>
            <p>But beſides, among and between theſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and others by Humane Impoſition and Invention, have brought in a vaſt Number of Holy-days, in Memory of the Apoſtles, and of their Saints, as they would call and make them. Now in this Caſe, if we would have all things done according to the Pattern ſhewed to us in the Goſpel, (ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 5.) we ſhould throw off, and ſurceaſe from the Obſervation of many, or moſt of theſe latter ſort, but therefore in no wiſe from the former. <hi>I ſpeak as unto wiſe Men, judge ye what I ſay.</hi> That is no good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment why we ſhould not Yearly Commemorate the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead, becauſe we would not willingly mind all the Saints Days in the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> nor yet in the <hi>Engliſh Almanack Calender.</hi> According to that Reaſoning, which may be gather'd from <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 23. Seeing that the firſt ſeems to be the Mind, and of the Inſtitution of God. This ought to be obſerved; but the other being the Tradition, Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Impoſition of Man, may be left unobſerved, and let alone. We ſhould be zealous for, and obſerve each thing, according as it is the Commandment and Inſtitution of God. But there is no ſuch Obligation as to what proceeds only from the <hi>Law of a Carnal Commandment,</hi> or from the Rudiments and Ordinances of Men.</p>
            <p>To ſhew and put a difference is one Eſſential Part of the Miniſterial Duty, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 26. And thus to put a difference between what is of Divine Inſtitution and Appointment; to ſhew a Difference between the Law and Commandment of God, and between the Orders and Impoſitions of Men: As alſo to point out both Extreams (for both Extreams are bad) and to ſhew how the Truth lies in the middle way be tween them both; All this Rightfully and Skilfully done, would prevent abundance of Errors and Miſtakes in Matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>True indeed, that now under the Goſpel Oeconomy and Diſpenſation, <hi>Holineſs unto the Lord,</hi> ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and intended in all the Actions of thoſe who would frame and order their Converſation according to the ſame Goſpel. And conſequently to a Chriſtian
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152400:6"/> 
               <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Woman,</hi> every day to him or her; not the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day only, but every Week Day alſo ſhould be <hi>Holineſs unto the Lord.</hi> And as every Day we draw nearer towards our End; and ſo we ought to grow better. Even ſo likewiſe we ſhould endeavour that we keep each day; to morrow more than this, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it be the Week Day, and this is Sabbath, more and more <hi>Holy unto the Lord;</hi> and try alſo if you can live the next Day yet more Holy, Sober, and Innocent, and ſo on. Nevertheleſs, as in the Six Days it is lawful to do worldly Work and Labour, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſerve God acceptably alſo, as on the Lord's Day in the Place of his Worſhip; which yet is not lawful to do on that. And as we read in the Scriptures of a double Portion, and of a double meaſure of the Spirit, of Pre-eminence and Excellency, that Chriſt in all things ſhould have the Pre-eminence; ſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, all this hinders not, that tho every Day unto a <hi>Chriſtian Man</hi> or <hi>Woman</hi> ſhould be <hi>Holy unto the Lord,</hi> yet nevertheleſs ſome particular Days, as thoſe <hi>Three Great Feſtivals</hi> before-mentioned, may be Holy above all the reſt, by way of Pre-eminence and Excellency.</p>
            <p>Having thus prepared the way, and ſhew'd the middle way between the too much ſuperſtitious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of Holy Days on one Hand, and the total Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect or Contempt of them on the other; <hi>Let no Man therefore judge you in Meat or in Drink, or in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of an Holy Day, or of the New Moon, or of the Sabbath Days, which are a Shadow of Things to come; but the Body is of Chriſt,</hi> Col. 2. 16, 17. The Apoſtle doth not here ſpeak to ſurceaſe the Uſe of them utterly, in no wiſe: But as thoſe great Holy days now in Uſe and Obſervation among us, have all a Relation and Tendency unto Chriſt, as his Nativity, his Suffering on the Croſs, His Reſurrection from the Dead, His Aſcenſion up to the Right Hand of God, and his ſending the Holy Ghoſt and Comforter on his Diſciples Apoſtles and Followers on the Day of <hi>Pentecost,</hi> and ſo in a leſs meaſure on each Day of our Aſſembling our ſelves together throughout the Year. Proceed we now to ſhew the right manner how to obſerve this Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, in the which our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt roſe from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152400:6"/> the Dead. As to which there cannot be a more fit, proper, and pertinent Text in all the Bible, than that we have choſen, <hi>If ye then be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is to be taken notice of, 1. a thing ſuppoſed, <hi>If ye then be riſen with Chriſt</hi> 2. A Direction given, <hi>Seek thoſe things which are above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the Words conſider'd all together is intimated forth that wrong manner of obſerving Feſtivals now in Uſe in the World; who look upon, and practice it no other than as a time of Feaſting and Idleneſs. But herein they forget the Benefits which Chriſt did for them at ſuch a time; as alſo what Duty is expecting from themſelves, as ariſing from thence.</p>
            <p>The Scripture, like the Author thereof, Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Word of God, doth effectually anſwer that true End of his Prieſthood, <hi>As to have Compaſſion upon the Ignorant, and thoſe who are out of the way.</hi> that is, to Heaven and Happineſs. The Scripture gives them Notice, and Warning, and Direction, to put them in the way again. Many of the Commandments and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in Scripture are ſilent Reproofs; for it often doth in an implied Manner take Notice of what is amiſs or wanting, in order to rightly inſtruct and make it up again. And ſo, where <hi>Paul</hi> by the Spirit ſpeaketh on this wiſe, <hi>If then ye be riſen with Christ;</hi> In that manner of Speech of his is contained an hidden In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuendo or Meaning, as if many were not riſen with Chriſt; for He writes unto theſe as the choice and beſt of Chriſtians, and thereby He implies that even they had made a good Proficiency and Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if even they had gone and proceeded ſo far, which can in no wiſe be ſaid of that mixed Multitude which is abroad in the World. Again, many do hear or read concerning the Reſurrection of Chriſt, but they do not at the very ſame time mind and give heed unto what Inſtruction and Application is to be made thereof unto themſelves; namely, <hi>That they alſo ſhould be riſen with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For altho People now living on the Earth are not put to Death on the Croſs, nor as yet laid in the Grave as He was, how then can they riſe with him? This
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152400:7"/> Queſtion is ſomewhat like that of <hi>Nicodemus</hi> in <hi>John</hi> 3. 4. and like that in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 35, 36. and ſo it is to be anſwer'd in like mauner. For as Jeſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>Nicodemus, Verily, verily I ſay unto thee, except a Man be born of Water, and of the Spirit, He cannot enter into the Kingdom of God;</hi> even ſo it is here, <hi>except a Man be riſen with Chriſt, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God, he can have no Benefits of Christ's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi> Marvel not at this, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>Ye muſt be riſen again with Chriſt;</hi> that is, as Chriſt was raiſed again in the Body, ſo ye muſt be raiſed again (even whilſt in Body) in your Spirit. As the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> explaineth himſelf elſewhere touching this matter; as Chriſt roſe from the Dead, even ſo we ſhould riſe up to newneſs of Life. And ſo the like Reaſon is to be learned from his Crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion. The Sixth Chapter of the <hi>Romans</hi> is full and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to this Purpoſe; <hi>Therefore we are buried with him by Baptiſm into Death; that like as Chriſt was raiſed up from the Dead by the Glory of the Father, even ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newneſs of Life. For if we have been planted together in the likeneſs of his Death, we ſhall be alſo in the likeneſs of his Reſurrection. Knowing this, that our old Mnn is crucified with him; that the Body of Sin might be deſtroyed. That henceforth we ſhould not ſerve Sin. For he that is dead is freed from Sin, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſt being raiſed from the Dead, dieth no more; Death hath no more Dominion over him. For in that he died, he died unto Sin once. But in that he liveth, he liveth unto God. Likewiſe reckon ye alſo your ſelves be dead indeed unto Sin, but alive unto God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> Rom. 6. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. And ſo to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude unto 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 44. Chriſt was raiſed again in his Natural Body, even in that Body of Fleſh which He brought from out of the Womb of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> and He carried about him more than Thirty Years, while the Lord Jeſus went in and out among us: So we ſhould be raiſed again with him in our Spiritual Body; that is, in thoſe Spiritual Qualifications, and Inward Endowments, which even now we have, and derive down from Chriſt our Head, altho He ſits on the Right Hand of God. <hi>There is a Natural Body,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152400:7"/> and there is a Spiritual Body,</hi> both in this our preſent State, as well as it will be ſo in the future Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And even now we are made up both of this Natural Body, and of this Spiritual Body; all one, and in like manner, as man is now made up of Body and Soul, all one, and in like manner, as <hi>there is a living Soul, and a quickening Spirit.</hi> The firſt gives Life here, and the latter is in order to Life hereafter: And this is that firſt Reſurrection which the Scriptures ſpeak of, particularly in that Great and Remarkable Place of the <hi>Revelations; Bleſſed is that hath his part in the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, upon ſuch the ſecond Death hath no Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From what hath been aforeſaid, may be perceived, the great Importance and Neceſſity of riſing with Chriſt; as alſo it hath been ſhewed from <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. what this riſing, and to be riſen with Chriſt, means; even to <hi>walk in newneſs of Life.</hi> For we know that when one is dead, and raiſed again, he hath thereupon a new Life, or another Life given unto him. And ſo Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould turn over a new Leaf, and run Counter to all the Thoughts, Words and Actions of their former natural unregenerate State. There is an Old, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Proverbial Saying, <hi>That People ſhould have ſomewhat new upon them at Eaſter.</hi> Which tho it be commonly underſtood of Cloaths and Garments, yet there is ſome Divine and Serious Truth contained therein, and to be gather'd from it. And that is, what was juſt now ſaid, now at this time our Thoughts are taken up with the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead, we ſhould alſo examine and prove our ſelves, whither <hi>we be riſen with him;</hi> and then queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on further, and look about, or rather from within our ſelves, whither <hi>we have any thing new on us,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within us.</p>
            <p>Do we walk in Newneſs of Life? And <hi>have we put off concerning the former Converſation, the old Man, which is corrupt according to the deceitful Luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? And have we put on the new Man, which after God is created in Righteouſneſs, and true Holineſs?</hi> There is a great Fault and Failure abroad in the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the too ſuperſtitious Obſervers of <hi>Lent</hi> and <hi>Holy-days;</hi> for many think that ſuch a Seaſon of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152400:8"/> Year is for Mortification and Repentance; (which Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification by the way is not a Popiſh Word, but a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Duty; <hi>Mortifie therefore your Members which are upon Earth,</hi> Col. 3. 5. for <hi>he that is dead is freed from Sin,</hi> Rom. 6. 7. Now Mortification ſignifies the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king dead, that is, unto Sin) whereas this ought to be a Chriſtian's Buſineſs all the Year round. And ſo I have read and heard that the Papiſts do obſerve their Carnival before <hi>Lent;</hi> wherein they give themſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unto Sin, and to all manner of Exceſs of Riot, like them of whom <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh; <hi>And behold Joy and Gladneſs, ſlaying Oxen, and killing Sheep, and drinking Wine. Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall die,</hi> Iſa. 22, 13. And ſo upon <hi>Shrove Tueſday</hi> they glut and make themſelves drunken, becauſe afterwards they muſt take up, and be very demure, and faſt. And ſo, after that is over again, they return to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Exceſs, and Gormandizing. There is too much of the Leaven and Remainder of this kind of Popery amongſt too many who call themſelves Members of the National Church of <hi>England;</hi> for the manner of many of them is to practiſe a Fit of Holineſs for a Seaſon. That is, to be in a ſerious Mood upon the Sabbath or Holy-Day: But then they are of the World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Vain and Ungodly manner of Spirit all the Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of their time. And this is like the putting on of new Cloaths at ſuch a Seaſon, and upon ſuch an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and then putting them off again. But all this and ſuch like, is not to walk in Newneſs of Life, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Meaning, and requiring of the Spirit of God. For to walk denotes a conſtant and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Poſture, which we abide in as often and as long as we move. It is ſuch a pace as holds on, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues in going. And ſo Life again is a conſtant and continuing thing, which abides whither we ſleep or wake, even as long as we breathe: So that to put theſe two together, it is certainly the Will of the moſt High God, that we his Creatures and Servants ſhould walk in Newneſs of Life as conſtantly and continually as we move, and breathe, and live; for the new Life is not a thing to be put on and off, to be changed, altered, or laid aſide upon every ſhift or turn;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152400:8"/> no more than we can deſtroy this natural Life, and raiſe it up again of our ſelves, without endangering or hurting it: This cannot be done. And tho many pretend to live or lead a new Life for a Seaſon, as a Day or a Week, or a Month, and then they leave it off again, and then they return to their old ways, like a Dog to his Vomit. But in ſuch the new Life was never truly or thoroughly ingrafted; but it was a Shadow or Repreſentation, and a Name only of the new Life. For the new Life, or the new Creature, is a more fixed and abiding thing than that amounts unto. But that the new Life is not to be laid down again, when it is once truly taken up; or when we are riſen with Chriſt, we are not to fall down again into the former worldly manner of Life. All this is ſignified by what is written, <hi>Knowing that Chriſt being raiſed from the Dead, dieth no more: Death hath no more Dominion over him,</hi> Rom. 6. 9. From which place the Inference is natural, eaſie, and neceſſary; that if we alſo be riſen with Chriſt, we muſt die to Sin no more. Death in Treſpaſſes and Sins ſhall have no more Dominion over us: And ſo from henceforth we ſhould <hi>reckon our ſelves to be always dead indeed unto Sin, but ever alive unto God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> if we would indeed have this Newneſs of Life avail unto Life for evermore. That to the Life we live here in the Body, there may ſucceed Glory hereafter. That the Seeds and Principles of Holineſs and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs being planted and rooted in us, even whilſt theſe Souls of ours are in theſe Bodies; ſo that at and againſt the Time when theſe Souls of ours go out, which will be when this Life, which is as a Vapour, and continueth not, is ended; there may ſucceed Glory and Immortality, and Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>To be thus riſen with Chriſt is the very Means that we may <hi>attain unto the Reſurrection of the Dead</hi> in that Good and Happy Senſe, ſpoken of in <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 11. and alſo this is that knowing of Chriſt, and the Power of his Reſurrection ſo ſignificantly expreſſed in the Verſe immediately foregoing. Saith the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Seeing that ye ſeek a Proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in you;</hi> and ſo this is the Proof of our being with Chriſt, if we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152400:9"/> have Chriſt ſpeaking in us, or actuating us, as the Soul doth the Body; or if we know Chriſt, and the Power of his Reſurrection effectually, and mightily raiſing us up to newneſs of Life, <hi>knowing that he who raiſed up our Lord Jeſus Christ, will alſo raiſe up our Mortal Bodies.</hi> And ſo the ſame God who raiſed up our Lord Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead, according to his Grace, which worketh in us mightily (provided we conſent and yield unto, and walk together with that ſame Grace) <hi>will raiſe us up alſo from the Death of Sin unto the Life of Righteouſneſs</hi> (which word Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, ſignifies a Conformity to all the Laws and Directions of that great Rule of Righteouſneſs in Scripture) or to the new Life: Which is ſo called in Oppoſition and Diſtinction unto that kind of Life which we did lead in our Natural and Unconverted State.</p>
            <p>Every one that underſtands the leaſt truly in the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God, doth alſo know thus much, That the Principal and only Drift and Deſign of the whole Scripture the Book of the Lord, is to promote a Righteous, Holy and Obedient Life in Men and Women. For throughout the ſame <hi>are Line upon Line, Line upon Line, Precept upon Precept, Precept upon Precept, here a little and there a little,</hi> and all to this ſame end: It is not only the Reſult and Concluſion of the whole Matter, but the Sum and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the whole Bible, both Law and Goſpel, both Old and New Teſtament. And if there be any other Commandment, and Words therein; it is all briefly comprehended in this Saying: Namely, <hi>Fear God, and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole Duty of Man.</hi> It is the whole, and all which God requires of Man; and tho God in his written Word, which we commonly call the Bible, doth therein ſpeak of this in divers Places, and ſundry Manners, and in different Words, yet they have all a Significancy and Tendency to this. <hi>The Grace of God,</hi> (whereby is meant and intended his written Word and Revelation, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and agreeing together, as in Water Face anſwereth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Face) <hi>hath appeared unto all Men, teaching us, that denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and Worldly Luſts, we ſhould live
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152400:9"/> Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly in this preſent World.</hi> And ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, ſpake by one and the ſame Spirit of God; and hence it is that they do all ſo wonderfully agree and meet together, like ſeveral Lines in a Center, in theſe things of Obedience, Godlineſs, Righteouſneſs, Holineſs, and Sobriety. To theſe particularly the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> inſtructs in, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts in all his Epiſtles, wherein He uſes more than a thouſand Words, which are all to the ſame Purpoſe; and ſo where He expreſſes it in one place, by being <hi>riſen with Christ.</hi> In another Place, by <hi>knowing of Chriſt, and the Power of his Reſurrection;</hi> in another Place, <hi>A proof of Chriſt ſpeaking in you;</hi> in another place He mentioneth <hi>A Being made Conformahle unto his Denth:</hi> Yea, he hath many ſuch kinds of Phraſe and Speech; they are all to the ſame Meaning and Signification, they do all carry infolden in them the ſame Inſtruction and Signification; namely, that we ſhould die unto Sin, and riſe again to newneſs of Life. And ſo, tho many Captious, Ignorant, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Hearers, are offended, and do find Fault with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions and Tautologies in Sermons, as to this the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh; <hi>To write the ſame things to me is not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, but to you it is ſafe.</hi> For he knew that it was a kind of making ſure Work in his teaching the way of Salvation. For one can never be put in Mind of a good thing too often, eſpecially of what is ſo abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to our Eternal Well-Being, Salvation, and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. To preach the ſame things over and over doth ſeem to People according as they are; for indeed it is not Grievous and Irkſome to Godly and Chriſtian Minds, to ſuch who ſeek diligently to go to Heaven, and would not miſs of it for all the World. For theſe know that <hi>Precept muſt be upon Precept, Precept upon Precept, Line upon Line, Line upon Line, here a little and there a little,</hi> Iſa. 28. 10. and all is little enough to bring them over unto God and good Things, we being by Nature ſo averſe towards him, and apt to forget him. But as for the Sinners and Tranſgreſſors, to whom this kind of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition is ſo nauſeous and weariſome, ſo it would be but once to mention that which they have no Mind to hear or know.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152400:10"/>
            <p>If I ſhould uſe more Words than what I have already to explain and make known unto you what it is to be <hi>viſen with Chriſt,</hi> I cannot truly, nor yet would I explain it otherwiſe than by Riſing again to Newneſs of Life, or that we ſhould live yet more unto God, and not to our ſelves; for this is the Reaſoning of the Apoſtle afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, <hi>for in that He died, He died unto Sin once, I but in that He liveth, He liveth unto God,</hi> Rom. 6. 10. And ſo as He purſues the ſame and like reaſoning elſewhere, <hi>no Man ſhould live unto Himſelf, but unto God who called him:</hi> And ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> reaſons after a like manner; <hi>For aſmuch then as Chriſt hath ſuffered for us in the Fleſh, Arm your ſelves likewiſe with the ſame Mind. For He that hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the Fleſh, hath ceaſed from Sin, that He ſhould no longer live the reſt of his time in the Fleſh, to the Luſts of Men,</hi> (nor yet to our own Luſt or Will) <hi>but to the Will of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 12. In the future Reſurrection of the Body, and after that, all they who ſhall be found worthy to obtain a Part and Portion therein, they will live unto God in a much more eminent and conſtant manner than any (even of his beſt Saints and Servants) in the Fleſh now do, or can do. Yea, God will be to them All in All: So in the firſt Reſurrection, which is in Order and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and Inſeparable Tendency unto that, we ſhould live unto God yet more than others do, or at leaſt it may be contrariwiſe with each of us, than what is written of the Wicked, <hi>God is not in all his Thoughts,</hi> Pſal. 10. 4. which may admit of a Twofold Conſideration, that God may be in ſome of his Thoughts, but not all of them; for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one doth think ſomewhat or other of God, but not to have him there for the moſt and greater part; this is a Contemper and rejecting of him; or ſecondly, amidſt all his Thoughts, which He hath about other things, the World, his Fellow-Creatures, and ſuch like God is not in all of them; that is, God is not at all, or very ſeldom in them. And this is yet a much greater Diſobedience and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for it is to be <hi>without God in the World,</hi> where is not a conſtant Senſe and awful Remembrance of, and Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction unto him. But indeed, if we live unto God, then God is in all our Thoughts; or for the moſt and greater part, for then the continual Bent, lifting up, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Soul, is unto him, that is Inviſible. And it is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152400:10"/> the continued Thought and Searching of our Heart, (without Ceaſing or Intermiſſion) how we may Obey, Serve and Glorifie him.</p>
            <p>It hath been aforeſaid, how that <hi>Paul</hi> by the Spirit lays it down as a thing ſuppoſed, as appears by the Particle, <hi>If ye be riſen with Chriſt;</hi> for He writes unto the <hi>Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> as unto real Chriſtians. And to ſuch only, to put in Mind of a Thing, and of a Duty, it is enough. For they will inſtantly do it, and ſet upon, and endeavour it. The Apoſtle doth ſuppoſe, and take it for Granted, that they had proceeded ſo far already, by taking the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, and the Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Redemption of Jeſus Chriſt, and thereupon He gives them Direction farther. But there is a vaſt difference between Real and Nominal Chriſtian; as alſo between Chriſtians formerly, and now adays: VVe read that in antient time; <hi>They that feared the Lord would of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſpeak one to another,</hi> Mal. 3. 16. <hi>And that they would ſpeak of the wonderful Works of God,</hi> Act. 2. 11. This was in common Converſation. And as theſe here in the <hi>Acts</hi> did it on the <hi>Day of Pentecoſt,</hi> ſo they would it more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially at the Time appointed, and upon their Solemn Feaſt Day. <hi>For this was a Statute in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the God of</hi> Jacob; That when they were to keep the Feaſt of the Paſſeover, and when their Children did ask what thoſe things did mean, they were to tell them, how the Lord in accompliſhing their Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> did ſlay the <hi>Egyptians</hi> Firſt-born, and did paſs over the Houſes of the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> VVen they did obſerve the Paſſeover, they did conſtantly talk of that their Deliverance, and praiſe God for it: But now adays People do keep the Feaſts of what is commonly called <hi>Chriſtmas, Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide,</hi> with the Leaven of Gluttony, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, Chambering, and VVantonneſs, in Vanity and Idleneſs, without ſpeaking one VVord in their ordinary Converſation; Beſides, what they hear perhaps out of the Sermons, or from the Scriptures read in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, out of Cuſtom and Formality) of the great Mercies of God vouchſafed to Mankind in their Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the Birth and Incarnation of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, ſending Him into the Fleſh, that He might deſtroy the VVorks of the Devil; His Death and Reſurrection, Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152400:11"/> and Deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt; theſe are only the ſit Topicks and Subjects of Diſcourſe at thoſe times; but yet they are quite out of Faſhion and Uſe among us, but it was not ſo in the Primitive Times. If Scholars do not as much mind their Books out of School as in School, they will not make any great Proficiency and Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Learning. And ſo we pretend to be Diſciples, (which word ſignifies Scholars) and Followers of Jeſus Chriſt. And in Truth, if we do not as much mind, yea, and obſerve our Duty to God and Chriſt as much; yea, more out of the Church and Congregation, or Aſſemblies of People for Worſhip, as when we are in them, for we are longer out than in, we ſhall never have that Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter and Denomination from God, as <hi>Daniel</hi> had, <hi>Thou art greatly beloved,</hi> Dan. 9. 23. or as it is in the Margent there, <hi>A Man of Deſires,</hi> or as <hi>John</hi> had, who is called the <hi>Beloved Diſciple.</hi> And ſo, if we were <hi>beloved of God,</hi> and of Chriſt, we ſhould have a Senſe, Manifeſtation, and Revelation of that their Love towards us; ſo that reciprocally and mutually our ſelves would love God, and Chriſt alſo. And it is a certain Rule, according to thoſe two Aphoriſms of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>They are of the World, therefore ſpeak they of the World. Out of the abundance of the Heart the Mouth ſpeaketh.</hi> That where the Love, Heart and Affection is moſt, People do uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally talk moſt of the ſame thing. And hence it is, that People talk ſo little of God, and of Heavenly things, for want of the Love of God in them; it is becauſe they do not ſeek the things above; for what one ſeeks after, He doth uſually talk of, and enquire after; and they do not ſet their Affections on Things above, but on Things on the Earth. Indeed one Reaſon why thoſe in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 11. did talk of the wonderful Works of God, becauſe that then they had been lately and newly done; and what is freſh, or a Novelty, this doth moſt commonly affect the Heart with Thought thereof, and fill the Mouth with Diſcourſe thereof. But tho the Creation of the World hath been Six Thouſand Years ſince, and the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mankind by Jeſus Chriſt, God manifeſted in the Fleſh, hath been accompliſhed well-nigh Seventeen Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years ſince, yet ſtill we ought to talk of theſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Works of God, and to declare theſe his Doings
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152400:11"/> among the People, continually praiſing Him for the ſame now at this day, as in the firſt Year after it was, if we had then lived. Yea, we ought to talk hereof, and praiſe him yet more and more, as we ſee the Day approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: In which we draw nearer in Time, when all theſe things ſhall be once more manifeſted before us. This is the right manner of keeping this Feaſt, when according to the Allowance given in <hi>Joel 2. 26. We ſhall eat and be ſatisfied</hi> (obſerve it is ſaid ſatisfied, not glutted or clogged, for the Righteous eateth to the ſatisfying of his Soul) <hi>and praiſe the Name of the Lord our God,</hi> eſpecially for theſe Great and Particular Mercies which He vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to Mankind at or about this Seaſon of the Year, remembring ſtill that we are to offer up an Offering of Praiſe to a Spiritual and an Holy Being, and to rejoyce, and be glad in the Lord our God. Which ſame Gladneſs and Rejoycing, if we ſhould go about to raiſe with the help of ſtrong Drink, as the manner of ſome is (but God forbid, and turn it from us) this would not be Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Joy, but Sinful Mirth. To ſuch Prophane Chriſtians it may be ſaid, <hi>Do ye thus requite the Lord, O fooliſh Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and unwiſe?</hi> By keeping the Feaſt (it is the Goſpel Phraſe, ſo that keeping of Feſtivals are certainly allow'd under the Goſpel Diſpenſation) with the Leaven of Sin and Wickedneſs. Is that your Tribute and Return of Praiſe, to tranſgreſs and provoke him yet more? Is that a Seaſonable Time of Rioting and Drunkenneſs, when you ſhould <hi>put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make not Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the Fleſh to fulfill the Luſts thereof,</hi> Rom. 13. 13. But now indeed the right manner of keeping the Feaſt is, To have nothing but Praiſes unto the Lord in our Heart and Tongue. It is ever ſeaſonable, but at this Return of the Year moſt eſpecially, to uſe thoſe VVords of <hi>Peter</hi> in our Mouth, and to have them in conſtant Remembrance within, <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to his abundant Mercy, hath begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us again unto a lively Hope, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead, to an Inheritance Incorruptible and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for you,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 3, 4.</p>
            <p>It being (as we are here told) reſerved in Heaven for us, our Duty thereupon is but Natural and Reaſonable, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152400:12"/> we ſhould in this ſhort mean while between, look and ſeek after it; which would be in the ſecond Place ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Direction given in our Text, <hi>Seek thoſe things which are above.</hi> We read in <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 10. of being made <hi>conformable unto the Death of Chriſt.</hi> Now there is a wonderful Conſequence, Connexion and Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Death and Reſurrection. Concerning his Death we read elſewhere on this wiſe, <hi>His Life is taken from the Earth,</hi> Acts 8. 33. <hi>If the Son of Man be lifted off from the Earth, then will He draw all Men unto him. This He ſpake, ſignifying by what Death He ſhould die.</hi> Now put all this together, His Life is taken off from the Earth; He is lifted off from the Earth: If we would be indeed made conformable unto his Death, What doth all this teach and inſtruct us in? Any one may gather and apprehend it; namely, That whilſt in Life our Life alſo ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off from the Earth, and that we ſhould be lifted off from the Earth in Soul and Mind, even whilſt the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Body is preſſed down, and confined unto the Earth; for it is no impoſſible Thing, as we by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence know, to have ones Body in one place, and ones Heart in another. And ſo a Chriſtian may, yea, he ought to have his Converſation in Heaven, even whilſt God hath determin'd the Bounds of his Habitation as yet (it is but for a very little while) on the Face of the Earth. That whilſt He moves and walks up and down here, and ſees the outſide of Heaven above, at a vaſt Diſtance and Height, yet in Mind and Soul He may enter within the Vail, and be upon the continued Thoughts, and moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Endeavour, how He may make ſure of, and ſecure a Reſt and Habitation for her there againſt the time ſhe ſhall be diſlodged off, and turn'd out from this <hi>Tabernacle of Clay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Abraham <hi>after that</hi> Lot. <hi>was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from him, lift up now thine Eyes, and look up from place where thou art Northward, and Southward, and Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and Weſtward; for all the Land which thou ſeest to thee will I give it, and to thy Seed for ever. Ariſe, walk thro the Land, in the length of it, and in the breadth of it, for I will give it unto thee,</hi> Gen. 13. 14, 15, 16. And ſo as <hi>Lot</hi> was ſeparated from him, if our Fellow-Creatures, and the things of this World were ſeparated from us, and we go upon a Mountain, or like <hi>Iſaac, into the Field to meditate.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152400:12"/> As we lift up our Eyes, and ſurvey the Heavens above in the height, in the length, and in the breadth of them, all things here below appear but as little, and inconſiderable, paltry, and trivial. They are Emphatically and diſtinctly called the <hi>Heavens of the Lord,</hi> Lam. 3. 66. <hi>When I conſider thy Heavens,</hi> Pſ. 8. 3. God hath reſerved theſe peculiarly to Himſelf. Tho He hath now ſeem'd to give the Earth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly to the Children of Men, whither they be good or bad; but <hi>His Heavens</hi> He will give only to ſuch who ſhall be found meet, and whom He ſhall judge worthy thereof. And ſo our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt doth diſcriminate and phraſe it on this wiſe; <hi>But they which ſhall be accounted worthy to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that World, and the Reſurrection from the Dead, Mat.</hi> 22. 30. They will not ſo far abuſe and love the World, as for the ſake thereof, either of the men, of the things therein, as to commit Sin, or omit Duty. And if we do neither of thoſe, then we may uſe the world ſafely enough. Indeed becauſe we are in the midſt thereof, we cannot but think, and ſee a little of it, do whatever we can. But as long as the Inviſible God, and how to pleaſe, and approve our ſelves unto him, that we may get his Favour and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, and Heaven above, takes up much the greater part of our Thought, Care, and Endeavour; then indeed we are ſo as is the Will and Requiring of God that we ſhould be; for then we live and act in Faith and by Faith. <hi>Not having received the Promiſes as yet</hi> (His Great, Glorious and future ones) <hi>but we now ſee them afar off, and are perſwaded of them, and do embrace them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that we are Strangers and Pilgrims on the Earth for they that ſay ſuch things, declare plainly that they ſeek a Country.</hi> And this is to ſeek thoſe things that are above. It is to have our Life taken off from the Earth, even whilſt we are in the midſt of Life. <hi>For the Life which we now live in the Fleſh, is by Faith in the Son of God, who loved and gave himſelf for me.</hi> And this is to be lifted off from the Earth, altho we are neither hung on the Croſs, not yet do fly in the Air. But if our Hearts and Souls are lifted up from, or above the things of the Earth, then we are lifted up alſo, and by this way God and Chriſt doth draw up our Souls unto Himſelf to Heaven above. <hi>Draw me</hi> (ſaith the Soul in the <hi>Canticles) and I will follow after thee.</hi> Now drawing is from one Place to another;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152400:13"/> and God doth draw up the Souls from Earth, unto Heaven.</p>
            <p>I hope that by declaring and delivering Sentences and Propoſitions of Truth, the foregoing Diſcourſe hath been Uſe or Uſeful all along; but however the Uſe thereof is manifold.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To teach us to have a great Indifferency, as to the Things of this World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To think much and continually upon the Place we are going unto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As <hi>Abraham</hi> had God ſpeaking unto him, and alſo a ſight of the Promiſed Land, when <hi>Lot was ſeparated from him.</hi> So we ſhould for ſome convenient time ſeparate our ſelves, even from our Wife and Children, Kinsfolks, and the Men of this World, from our neceſſary Family Concerns, and our Buſineſs in the World, in order to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy more cloſe Communion with God, and ſeek the things above.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As we read or hear any of the things of God, we ſhould inſtantly make Application thereof unto our ſelves As when we read or hear of the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt; this ſhould apply and bring it home to our ſelves, as to examine and prove our ſelves alſo, <hi>If we be riſen with Chriſt.</hi> For every Article of Faith doth carrv a Word of Inſtruction in it; and in each wonderful Work which God hath done for the Children of Men, is infold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and contained a Duty of us towards him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. What hath been aforeſaid ſhould teach us to beware of Extreams.
<q>Dum vitant ſtulti vitia in contraria currunt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But to go on in the way of God's Commandments, not turning aſide from them to the Right Hand, nor to the Left; avoiding too much Superſtion on one Hand in the Obſervance of the meer Ordinances of Men; as alſo the Neglect and Contempt of the Inſtitutions of God on the other.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
